<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>timeseries on Magic Sand</title>
    <link>https://tcolgate.github.io/categories/timeseries/</link>
    <description>Recent content in timeseries on Magic Sand</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-GB</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://tcolgate.github.io/categories/timeseries/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Prometheus: Apdex alerting (Qubit Eng Blog)</title>
      <link>https://tcolgate.github.io/blog/prometheus-apdex-alerting-qubit-eng-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tcolgate.github.io/blog/prometheus-apdex-alerting-qubit-eng-blog/</guid>
      <description>Note: This was originally posted on the Qubit Engineering Blog), and CopyRight is, at the time of writing, owned by Coveo. It was written, and illustrated, by me, but would have been unreadable but for input and editing by my fantastic teammates.
I’m going to take a break from our series on Production Kubernetes to write up a couple of smaller articles on Prometheus. This article will give an overview of Apdex, and go on to describe a practical approach to implementing Apdex alerts in Prometheus.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Seasonality in Prometheus alerting (Qubit Eng Blog)</title>
      <link>https://tcolgate.github.io/blog/using-seasonality-in-prometheus-alerting-qubit-eng-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tcolgate.github.io/blog/using-seasonality-in-prometheus-alerting-qubit-eng-blog/</guid>
      <description>Note: This was originally posted on the Qubit Engineering Blog, and CopyRight is, at the time of writing, owned by Cove. It was written, and illustrated, by me, but would have been unreadable but for input and editing by my fantastic teammates.
In this post, we will show a worked example of building a Prometheus alert for a typical user facing service.
Introduction At Qubit we have recently completely
a migration from our legacy Shinken and Graphite based monitoring to a system built around Prometheus, a modern time series database.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time Series Search in Prometheus</title>
      <link>https://tcolgate.github.io/blog/time-series-search-in-prometheus/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tcolgate.github.io/blog/time-series-search-in-prometheus/</guid>
      <description>Note: This post describes an extension to Prometheus that is unlikely to ever make it upstream, and definitely not in its current form.
Time Series Indexing When we talk about an index for a time-series database, we are usually talking about an index of the metadata. In the case of Prometheus, such an index would help us locate all the series with certain labels, allowing us to quickly query, for example, all the http_requests_total timeseries that match a given handler or response code.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
