<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>monitoring on Magic Sand</title>
    <link>https://tcolgate.github.io/categories/monitoring/</link>
    <description>Recent content in monitoring on Magic Sand</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-GB</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://tcolgate.github.io/categories/monitoring/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Prometheus: K8s Cronjob alerts (Qubit Eng Blog)</title>
      <link>https://tcolgate.github.io/blog/prometheus-k8s-cronjob-alerts-qubit-eng-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tcolgate.github.io/blog/prometheus-k8s-cronjob-alerts-qubit-eng-blog/</guid>
      <description>Note: This was originally posted on the Qubit Engineering Blog Coveo. It was written, and illustrated, by me, but would have been unreadable but for input and editing by my fantastic teammates.
Kubernetes Jobs and Cronjobs are powerful tools that present some interesting challenges to monitoring. We’ll demonstrate rules using kube-state-metrics and Prometheus to monitor and alert on failed jobs. We’ll discuss how the rules were formulated, and how to leverage Prometheus label matching techniques for advanced alerting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prometheus: Apdex alerting (Qubit Eng Blog)</title>
      <link>https://tcolgate.github.io/blog/prometheus-apdex-alerting-qubit-eng-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tcolgate.github.io/blog/prometheus-apdex-alerting-qubit-eng-blog/</guid>
      <description>Note: This was originally posted on the Qubit Engineering Blog), and CopyRight is, at the time of writing, owned by Coveo. It was written, and illustrated, by me, but would have been unreadable but for input and editing by my fantastic teammates.
I’m going to take a break from our series on Production Kubernetes to write up a couple of smaller articles on Prometheus. This article will give an overview of Apdex, and go on to describe a practical approach to implementing Apdex alerts in Prometheus.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
